Guide to the Colonel John Brown and Major General Preston Brown Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Colonel John Brown and Major General Preston Brown papers
1763-1865
MS 105
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
(2 boxes, 1 folio)
Largely family correspondence of the Brown, Preston and Mason families received by Reverend John Brown of Virginia and his sons, John, Samuel and James. Most important are the eleven letters from John Brown, member of the Continental Congress and senator from Kentucky (1792-1805), which discuss the Constitution, the Missouri Compromise and the episode in Kentucky history known as the "Spanish Conspiracy". Letters from James Brown were written from Paris (1823-1833) when he was United States ambassador to France, while those from Samuel Brown describe events in Mississippi in the 1810s and 1820s. Margaretta (Mason) Brown is represented by a commonplace book, reading list and poems.
Brown, John, 1757-1837
Arrangement
Arranged in three boxes: Boxes 1 and 2 contain correspondence, sermons, poems, and miscellaneous papers. Box 3 contains Photographs.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the heirs of Major General Preston Brown, 1948.
Scope and Contents
The Colonel John Mason Brown and Major General Preston Brown Papers consist of ten inches of letters, sermons, poems, photographs, and miscellaneous papers of the Rev. John Brown of Virginia (1728-1803); his sons John II (1757-1837), Samuel (1769-1830), James (1766-1835), and Preston (1775-1826); his son John's wife, Margaretta (Mason) Brown (1772-1838); and their sons Mason (1799-1867; Y. 1820) and Orlando (1801-1867). Colonel John Mason Brown (1837-90; Y. 1856) is represented by an incoming letter and a printed copy of a photograph; Major General Preston Brown (1872-1948; Y. 1892), by a single photograph. There are biographical sketches of John II, Samuel, and James in the Dictionary of American Biography. Mason Brown, John Mason Brown, and Major General Preston Brown appear in their respective Yale classbooks.
The letters in the Brown Papers were received mainly by the Rev. John Brown and by his sons John, Samuel, and James. They were written by members of the Brown, Preston, and Mason families and by various men who were prominent in national and regional public life, including James Monroe, Henry Clay, James Wilkinson, and Charles Ingersoll. The letters span from 1763 to 1865, but they are concentrated in the 1790s. Many of the letters from that decade deal with the episode in Kentucky history known as the "Spanish Conspiracy." Other letters deal with personal matters, with the development of Kentucky, and with such national issues of the day as the Constitution and the Missouri Compromise. The letters by James Brown include news from Paris, where he served as U.S. Ambassador between 1823 and 1833, and some of those by Samuel Brown contains news of Alabama and Mississippi in the 1810s and 1820s. A list of correspondents follows the box list, and the letters are catalogued individually in the department's manuscript catalog.
The sermons are by the Rev. John Brown and by an unidentified Presbyterian minister of Virginia in the eighteenth century. The poems are by Margaretta (Mason) Brown.
Biographical / Historical
John Brown: Senator, Kentucky legislator; studied at Princeton; one of the Rockbridge soldiers under Lafayette; continued education at William and Mary; studied law with Thomas Jefferson; active in the process of securing statehood for Kentucky; U.S. Senator for Kentucky, 1792-1805.
List of Correspondents
American Colonization Society. Kentucky --- (1)
Beale, Samuel --- (1)
Beckley, John --- (5)
Belli, John, 1760-1809 --- (1)
Blackburn, [S ]? --- (1)
Bodley, Thomas --- (1)
Bradford, Joseph N. --- (1)
Breckenridge, James, [1768-1833]? --- (2)
Brodhead, Daniel, Jr., 1736-1809 --- (1)
Brown, James, 1766-1835 --- (33)
Brown, Rev. John, 1728-1803 (1 folder of sermons) --- (2)
Brown, John, 1757-1837 --- (11)
Brown, J. P. W. --- (1)
Brown, Margaretta (Mason), 1772-1838 --- (13)
Brown, Mary (Yoder) --- (1)
Brown, Mason 1799-1867 (Yale 1820) --- (4)
Brown, Preston W., d.1826 --- (3)
Brown, Samuel, 1769-1830 --- (27)
Burr, Aaron, 1756-1836 --- (1)
Caldwell, Charles, 1772-1853 --- (1)
Campbell, Archibald --- (1)
Campbell, Arthur --- (2)
Campbell, David --- (1)
Capin, Nathaniel W. --- (1)
Carondolet, Francisco Louis Hector, baron de, ca. 1748-1807 --- (1)
Cartwright, Justinian --- (1)
Clark, Elizabeth --- (1)
Clay, Henry, 1777-1852 --- (7)
Coleman, William --- (1)
Coxe, Tench, 1755-1824 --- (1)
Craddock, Robert --- (1)
Craighead, Thomas Brown, -1825 --- (1)
Crockett, Joseph --- (1)
Croghan, George, 1791-1849 --- (1)
Croghan, William --- (2)
Dayton, Jonathon, 1760-1824 --- (2)
Duncan, John M. --- (4)
Edgar, John T. --- (1)
Farnham,? --- (1)
Gamble, Robert --- (1)
Garrard, James, 1749-1822 --- (1)
Gordon, A. G. --- (1)
Green, Berryman --- (1)
Hamilton, Alexander, 1757-1804 --- (1)
Hancock, George --- (1)
Hart, Thomas --- (1)
Henley, Sam --- (1)
Hughes, James --- (1)
Humphreys, Mary (Brown) --- (2)
Ingersoll, Charles --- (10)
Innes, Harry, 1752-1816 --- (3)
Jackson, Dr. Samuel, 1787-1852 --- (1)
Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826 --- (1)
Knox, Major General Henry, 1750-1806 --- (1)
Logan, Benjamin, 1743-1802 --- (1)
McCraw, Samuel? --- (1)
McIntosh, William --- (1)
Madison, James, 1750/1-1836 --- (3)
Mason, Catherine Van Wyck --- (2)
Mason, Rev. John --- (1)
Mason, John Mitchell, 1770-1829 --- (2)
Monroe, James, 1758-1831 --- (5)
Morehead, Charles Slaughter, 1802-1868 --- (1)
Morrison, James --- (2)
Mosby, John --- (1)
Mosby, L. Jr. --- (1)
Mosby, Robert --- (1)
Mosby, Wade --- (5)
Nicholson, Marie --- (1)
Oneall, Abijah --- (1)
Overton, John, 1766-1833 --- (1)
P, O? --- (1)
Percy, Thomas G. --- (1)
Pindell, Richard --- (1)
Pogue, George --- (1)
Poussin, William Tell --- (1)
Preston, Frank Francis, 1765-1836 --- (6)
Preston, J. --- (2)
Preston, William, 1816-1887 --- (1)
Randolph, John, of Roanoke, 1773-1833 --- (2)
Saidler, James --- (1)
St. Clair, Arthur, 1736-1818 --- (1)
Seitz, John A. --- (1)
Shelby, Isaac, 1750-1826 --- (1)
Smith, John --- (1)
Speed, James, 1812-1887? --- (1)
Steele, William --- (1)
Swan, James, 1754-1830 --- (2)
Templeton, Maria --- (1)
U.S. Army. re John Belli --- (1)
U.S. Army (Maj. John Adair, 1757-1840) --- (1)
U.S. Army (John Belli, 1760-1809) --- (2)
U.S. Army (Michael Rudolph?) --- (1)
U.S. Army (Maj.Gen. Anthony Wayne, 1745-1796) --- (5)
U.S. Army (Brig.Gen. James Wilkinson, 1757-1825) --- (17)
U.S. Commissioners to negotiate with the Indians North of the Ohio [Benjamih Lincoln 1735-1810;Beverly Randolph; and Timothy Pickering, 1745-1829, Commissioners] --- (1)
U.S. Senate --- (1)
U.S. Treasury. Register's Office --- (1)
Van Cortlandt, Charles --- (1)
Varick, J. D. --- (1)
Varick, Margaretta --- (1)
Varick, Theodore V. W. --- (1)
Virginia. Governor, 1776-1779, 1784-1785 (Patrick Henry) --- (1)
Virgina. Governor, 1792-1795, (Henry Lee) --- (1)
Wallace, David, 1799-1859 --- (1)
Warren, John --- (1)
Washington, Bushrod, 1762-1829 --- (1)
Watts, Edward and E. B. --- (1)
Wilkinson, James Birg. Gen., 1757-1825 --- (39)
Williamson, Hugh, 1735-1819 --- (2)
Wilson, William --- (2)
Winn, John --- (2)
Woods, Archibald --- (1)
Worthington, S.? --- (1)
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Armed Forces; Missouri compromise; Music; Women poets; Alabama -- History; Kentucky -- History; Mississippi -- History; Paris (France) -- History -- 1789-1900; Southern States; United States -- Foreign relations; Poems; Politicians; Soldiers; Brown, John, 1728-1803; Brown, John, 1757-1837; Brown, Margaretta Mason, 1772-1838; Brown, Mason, 1799-1867; Brown, Preston W., 1775-1826; Brown, Preston, 1872-1948; Brown, Samuel, 1769-1830; Clay, Henry, 1777-1852; Dayton, Jonathan, 1760-1824; Garrard, James, 1749-1822; Hamilton, Alexander, 1757-1804; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826; Madison, James, 1751-1836; Mason, John M. (John Mitchell), 1770-1829; Monroe, James, 1758-1831; Preston, Francis, 1765-1835; Randolph, John, 1773-1833; Wilkinson, James, 1757-1825; Yale College (1718-1887). Class of 1820; Yale College (1718-1887). Class of 1856; Yale College (1887- ). Class of 1892; Yale University -- Students
- Inventory, 1763-(1783-1841)-1865
  - Correspondence and miscellaneous papers, 1763-1809 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and miscellaneous papers, 1810-1865, undated (Box 2, Folder 33-61)
  - John Brown (1728-1803)
    - Sermons, 1752-1794, undated (Box 2, Folder 62-63)
  - Sermons of an unidentified 18th century Virginia Presbyterian minister, Undated (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Margaretta (Mason) Brown
    - Commonplace book and reading list, 1798 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Poems, 1802-1817, undated (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 3)